hi everybody welcome to the bnb
connection
this is episode five or six brad i can't
remember
this six six episode six
and we decided to do this on tempo
now this is our like third or fourth
time recording this because we had
issues with
camtasia so uh now we're using
screenflow
so hopefully this works this time around
all right so first of all uh
bradley explain what tempo training is
and give an example
yeah tempo training is varying the tempo
uh that the cadence that you lift at so
the classic way that it's often
discussed is in four
numbers first number would be the
eccentric the second number would be the
whole
the time you spend in the neutral
position
uh then the third number would be the
concentric and the last number would be
the time you spend in the neutral
position
top of the concentric so for instance if
it was 3-0-1-0
it would be a three-second negative no
seconds in the neutral position
no isometric hold one second on the
concentric and then no
seconds again in the isometric portion
um and this is a standard way that we've
been
that you'll see in textbooks as well as
in many magazines is looking at tempo
so let me further elaborate on that
because brad was making up his own
language they're
saying neutral position he means the
isometric position
so um say i'm doing a military press
okay
i if i'm doing tempo training and it is
what's the example use four zero two
zero four
three one oh yeah four two or whatever
4020. oh so say i'm starting up top
i would go one two three
four zero seconds here one
two zero and then go right back down
so you could have an unlimited
combination here
say you did two one two one you would go
one two one one
two one just like that so
you see these in articles tempo
recommendations
um where various experts will tell you
what tempo to use
now uh just to give kind of a
refresher the first time i ever heard
about tempo training was from charles
poliquin
i so i i'm gonna credit him for
popularizing it because i never heard of
it before him
um some of our friends bradley some of
our good
colleagues use this joe daudel likes
tempo training
um and then there are other experts like
uh
christian thibaut and chad waterbury
they always say lift as explosively as
possible um
before we get into the research do you
use
tempo training uh have you used well
first of all how long did you own a gym
for
18 years 15 years 18 years you owned a
gym
as a trainer did you do a lot of seven
ways so
that's why i'm so i look so young
you started when you were six years old
so did you as a trainer did you do a lot
of tempo training
i have experimented with it a little bit
over time i have gravitated towards not
using it in my personal
approach and this is based this is
evidence-based based
not only on what we know we're talking
about the research yeah just talk about
what you did
so dude i i'm i'm getting there the
research is
the research at this point is very
equivocal and not well done
we can get into the specifics but also
on a lot of personal experience so
my general approach at this point is to
perform repetitions quickly
and uh that really depends
as it always does my favorite phrase in
fitness is it depends
but if you are a strength or power uh
athlete your goal should be to move
explosively
like you would mention that chad
woodaberry and some others uh describe
because that's the goal this what's that
christianity
that is the uh goal of the the actual
sport or or the activity where you're
looking to move something else
even in strength so if your goal is
strength you're going to try to move the
weight explosively it's going to move
very slowly by nature if you're
performing a 1 2
3 rm you're not going to be able to move
that weight very quickly it's going to
go up in a 2 second
or even more 2 3 4 if you're really
doing a true one rm i could take four
seconds to complete that
but you're not in intentionally it has
to do with the intense you're not
intentionally slowing it down
from a bodybuilding perspective my focus
is more on the control
of the lift so looking at it from a time
perspective to me is really irrelevant
but what i try to uh have the competitor
do or the
individual who's looking for hypertrophy
do is to focus on the feel of the weight
and really focus on the mind to muscle
connection
so if you're coming up you focus on just
squeezing and if that takes a second or
two seconds
it's really kind of irrelevant i think
it's probably a one to two second
positive contraction uh and eccentric is
roughly the same thing so you're talking
anywhere from two to four seconds total
rep
and no uh no isometric hold on the
neutral
in the neutral positions
neutral this as opposed to this or this
neutral meaning not going concentric or
eccentric
um yeah you're making up terminology
here
quit being a guru um okay so
uh i have a
bone to pick there i bet you you
mentioned
one or two seconds i bet you if you went
to gyms around the world
and you really looked at the tempo most
people do a one second
concentric and a one second eccentric
and they do
you know a repetition takes two seconds
i would say worldwide that's probably
the norm do you agree
you know probably i don't think it
matter again the
exact time how long it takes doesn't
matter if when you're focusing on that
squeeze
it has to do with getting not really a
mind to muscle connection so
part of it is how long the repetition is
uh you get a shorter repetition and
something like a curl than you're going
to do in a lat pull down
to me the timing is irrelevant you know
if i'm feeling that weight how long did
that take i mean i'm coming down feeling
my muscle
what was that second second and a half
it's not real
but the actual time is the reason why i
wanted to bring that up is because
if people are really doing one second up
one second down
and and we're telling them to do four
seconds down and two seconds up
we're telling them to lower it four
times slower than they're used to
and to lift two times slower than
they're used to essentially the
the whole entire rep would be would take
three times as long so we're telling
they're doing two seconds who's weak are
you telling them that they should be
doing a two at four and two
no i'm not good okay so so what i will
say is
is that most people who are training for
hypertrophy are not
do not get a good mind to muscle
connection and that is a big issue
with why a lot of people don't get their
optimal results
that a lot of people just focus on
swinging up the weights
and they're not really feeling the
muscle work as much as they should be
so that to me is much more the issue
than focusing on
if you're focusing on the time then
you're not focusing on the muscle
so it's just not the way you should be
going about it if your goal is
hypertrophy like i said from a
power lifting or strength standpoint the
focus should be on moving the weight
quickly
that there the time is much more
relevant it should be an explosive when
i say quickly
explosively that's an explosive lift
because that's what the goal of the
movement is so talk about the research
what does research have to say about
this topic
yeah so the research is very equivocal i
mean there are studies it's really all
over the place and this
really comes down to the flaws in the
methodologies used it's hard to design
studies in this context it also has to
do with the modalities that are used
the majority of it is done on isokinetic
machinery like an isokinetic dynamometer
which controls the speed of repetition
but that does not necessarily equate to
what we call
isotonic movement using free weights or
cables
uh they they're not necessarily
correlated in terms of how they apply
because on an isokinetic dynamometer
you are getting a resistance when you're
moving it's forcing you into a
a given speed whereas in
the isotonic type movements your
movement is controlled by
it's going to be dictated by gravity so
let me let me elaborate on that a little
bit
so i used a isokinetic dynamometer
when i was in auckland and i love them
they're great but
um you can use them for testing and for
training
so like say i was doing elbow flexion
and i'm in this dynamometer i can
control the speed
so it's gonna have constant tension on
your you know
arm coming up and down you can control
the speed and you're pushing as hard as
you can
so well i wouldn't say constant tension
it's a constant speed but you're putting
as much force as you can against it or
as much torque as possible
um throughout that speed
and again you can use it for testing
people and so you can show
that they did this training and then
they improved their
rate of torque development or their
torque production at this speed or
whatever
or you can use it for training but the
problem is
like less than one percent of you know
like our listeners
probably none of our listeners will have
access to a dynamometer so
this is special this is kind of like
research for researchers
it doesn't it's not very meaningful for
our field
so the the problem with most of the
research you're saying is that
a lot of it is on isokinetic
dynamometers and not
as much research on barbell like iso
inertial training but there are studies
on iso inertial training and what do
they
if you had to summarize it what would
you say
i'd summarize they're conflicting that
some show
because again a lot depends upon how you
design a study so i mean there's a
classic study by a tenemodo
where they equated they did a three
second
up and three second down versus a
traditional one in one cadence
uh and found similar results from muscle
hypertrophy and strength measures
but they the weight was at a different
level and the sample sizes are small
so you just get different there's
differences in the uh
some results show some better results
with slower training some results
show better results with faster training
for the most part if you're looking for
speed for
power the literature pretty much does
show that faster training does
promote better results for the most part
um
believe in that there's some conflicting
aspects of research again just
in flaws and research design okay so
um i will
now discuss how i use it in my training
um and i'll just talk a little bit about
tempo
just offer some some random thoughts
so i never in my
the way i work out and the way i train
clients i never
will tell them like i'll never give them
instructions on the concentric or the
eccentric
i will have them pause a lot i do a lot
of pause reps
um and isometric holds so like when they
do hip thrusts the hardest part is at
the top
so i will have them i want them to you
know make sure they're using full range
of motion
and a lot of times on the last rep of
their last set i have them hold it to
for five to ten seconds because that's
the hardest part it builds good habits
it also it's a great way to induce
metabolic stress you get a big burn
holding it there
so and they would have just stopped the
set there but i make them
hold it there at the top so it's a way
to extend the set
um now the way i think of tempo though i
don't
i personally think that that can
interfere with
the productivity of the set if you're
trying to count
you know you have a self-selected
cadence that's going to give you
the best results and when you start
veering from that and start focusing on
counting rather than the lifting
i think that you can interfere a little
bit now
that doesn't mean i just always lift as
explosively as possible it depends on
the goal
i'm not trying to do seated rows as fast
as possible i'm trying to squeeze the
peak contraction the end range you know
when i do seated rows you know you want
to come and squeeze and hold
hold that position for a second before
returning so it's not about being
as fast as possible so some exercises
have
increasing strength curves like squats
you're weak at the bottom and you're
stronger at the top
you could also say they have descending
torque angle curves
so with a squat you explode up but the
top range of the movement
is light so some studies have shown that
when you do explode
when you do lift as fast as possible
with sub maximal weight
what happens is you have this burst of
muscle activation
you spring the weight up and then about
halfway through the lift you start
decelerating because
you know otherwise if you didn't you'd
be curling like this and it would like
drill you you know or like you'd squat
and you'd leave the ground
and you'd have these jarring forces so
in that situation i think of it more as
instead of like dynamite you could say
dynamic effort and
compensatory acceleration training is
the same thing
but really they're different um to me
with dynamic effort you're trying to
move as fast as humanly possible
with compensatory acceleration training
you're just kind of
to me that implies a more smooth you try
to lift more explosively
as the weight gets easier in things like
squats and deadlifts
so you're just ex like compensating for
the mechanical advantage by lifting more
explosively
however you can also use accommodating
resistance so bands and chains
my problem with bands and chains is that
most people use too heavy of weight with
bands and chains and
i think it's best when you use just
enough to let you keep accelerating that
weight for longer
so muscle activation stays high and
doesn't shut down
um and in most of the studies on band
that first of all there's tons of
research on bands and chains
and they show almost all the studies
show
favorable results in comparison to
traditional training
which could be because it's novel but i
don't think so i think there is an
advantage
but most of the studies use only like
you know say ten percent
of one rep max for band and chain ten
tension that they don't go too heavy so
i like bands and chains for that but
also it what boils down to it all
depends on the lift
say i'm doing deadlifts i think you
should pull explosively but
but if you're doing dynamic effort with
fifty percent your one rep max
you'll find that you burst up and you
could like so you try to squeeze the
glutes and i don't it's hard to explain
but
you can you can do explosive deadlifts
in a way that's not
jarring by like pushing your hips
forward
with squats i don't want to leave the
ground you know i don't want to keep
accelerating to the point where i jump
off the ground you accelerate and then
you kind of
slow it down at the end um
you know like chin ups uh
trying to think of exercise like rowing
movements i try to squeeze the end range
curls you try to squeeze the end tricep
extension squeeze the end
you know what i mean basically hold on
let me just squeeze in the end
because i i'm a big fan of that that
does not necessarily
you for me i'm not holding that for a
second
squeezing the end i'm squeezing the end
and then coming i mean it's feel when
you're feeling a muscle throughout
you're squeezing you're basically
squeezing throughout the entire
movement but that end gets a little
extra i guess because it's in an
isometric
um a isometric uh component at that
point where you're
at a place where it's one second right
to talk about it as
a tempo i think really that's the issue
with me is that that's
where it's not like all right one okay
now i'm coming in it's just
and that's the bodybuilder how are you
talking about hypertrophy yeah totally
agree
it's a hypertrophy thing so it's not
it's not about tempo now again i think
that's where the misnomer for me comes
in
that we shouldn't be counting these
things it's about the
when it comes to hypertrophy it's not
the feel when it comes to training
uh for power and strength it's about
explosiveness and i'll tell you another
thing
when you uh when when you tell a client
to pause for a full second
they won't if you tell them to pause for
three seconds they'll pause for one
second if you tell them to pause for
five they'll pop for three because what
they do is
they start counting before they've
locked out so like
i've always thought if i really want
them to pause for three full seconds
because three full seconds
this 1001 1002
1003 that's a long pause
and they won't do that if you tell them
pause for three seconds they'll really
pause for one
and if you tell them pause for five
they'll really pause for three
so i i adjust for that but you're right
when it's just the feel
you don't even hold it for a full second
it's just reaching end range and kind of
squeezing
that's not affecting tempo too much but
it's not
lifted because to me if you lift as fast
as
humanly possible then every set of bench
press you would
you jar up top every set of squats
no no but see this is the thing yeah but
you'd only be doing that if let's say
you're a strength
athlete the weight that you're going to
use you're not moving it that quick so
if you're a strength athlete
you're training with five reps generally
and below five rm
the forearm three arm there's no way
you're going to jar yourself because by
the time you're
you're getting up it's going to be a
slow rep even let's say your five rep
how fast do you move in a five rep uh
your first rep on a five rep
uh max you're still moving it it may be
a second and a half i mean it's not
not so i see your point but i okay
picture push-ups if you really were
exploding as fast as possible in a
push-up you'd do a plyometric push-up
push-up but you can do explosive
push-ups
by kind of like coming down reverse it
very fast be very explosive when you
reverse it and then you kind of chill
coast to the top a little bit you don't
leave the ground
that gives a very good stretch
shortening cycle so it's good for
athletics but you don't have to be
jarring
if you wanted why not do the plyometric
if you want to do plyometric push-ups
you do those separately
but one study showed that because one
study showed that you get more
uh i think it was ischiera or something
we reviewed it brad in our
i think we did in our push-up article
for sdj but you got more
uh force and i don't know if they
measured force or impulse or rate of
force development but they had when you
didn't leave the ground
so i started practicing with that and i
saw when you
when you leave the ground you have a
slower and then you end up exploding
towards the top
but if you just do a very fast cadence
push-up you end up
the reversal is quicker and you produce
more ground reaction forces
anyway i could be wrong about that i
i think i remember that right remember
that study but okay
um well considering i did most of that
paper and you just rode my coattails
just kidding that's still
so wrong if that was the case
i don't think i could have any i've
teamed up with you with almost every
paper i've published because you do
you make them 50 times better um anyway
uh
so um anyway but the point is
um i'm never in my training or when i
train i'm never counting the eccentric
or the concentric
do you think that it could interfere
with the results by
counting you're focusing on something
other than the
you know well that's what exactly so i i
think that
really the issue with this is is that
the
from a hypertrophy perspective as i said
before it comes down to feel and
certainly if you're counting you're not
it's going to interfere with your
thought and from a strength and power
you have to be focused on moving the
weight not about if you're focused on
counting
again it's going to diminish i could
never see
focusing on on really maximizing my
strength or power where i'm counting out
or up i just don't do it
now i have experimented with especially
with some beginner clients
early on in my career i just didn't find
again i think it took away from their
focus of form
in that context really that's where i
had thought the application might be in
in some of the newer clients who's just
trying to
focus on the form and you're going okay
think about the smoothness rather than
and it just
didn't work well it didn't i gravitated
towards a more natural approach where
they're focusing on the weight the form
whatever it is yep okay two more topics
we should discuss
um one is the speed of the eccentric
contraction now if you
look at all the research i would say
that
um the body of evidence in in terms of
what's more important for muscle growth
if you had to choose one the concentric
phase or the eccentric phase
if you could only do concentrics or
eccentrics the rest of your life
i would choose eccentrics based on the
resources either
like if you're on a beach and you're
looking at brad you can only do one
exercise the rest of your life what
would it be
no so it's got to be the hip for us
so uh the eccentric component
would you agree that if you look at the
i know
a lot of times the the like the studies
aren't work
matched and things like that or volume
equated but when you do
the the differences aren't as big but
the eccentric is
every bit as important as the concentric
phase if not more would you agree
yeah at the very least it's as important
and
uh there's actually been a recent made
analysis that showed there actually was
a slight advantage
how much of it is due to a difference in
work matched
uh in the work that's done is equivocal
but
yeah i would completely agree and by the
way there's also differential
you get different responses between
concentric and essential so they
actually
produce different aspects of hypertrophy
they work through different mechanisms
so um so
the so we both agree that the eccentric
phase is very important now
here's what's interesting about
eccentric contractions when you do a
concentric contraction the faster the
velocity
the less force i can produce so the
slower if i'm isometric and i'm pushing
as hard as i can
i can produce the most force as i go
faster and then you know when i go real
fast
i can produce less force because that's
um you know that's
that's you know in concordance with the
force velocity curve
but eccentric contractions are different
with eccentric contractions the faster
you go
the more force you can produce so the
graph kind of looks like this
with concentric being slower but but
eccentric being faster if that makes any
sense so this side
with concentric the faster you go the
more force that you can produce
so does this mean that we should be
producing fast decent we should we
should be doing fast eccentrics or slow
eccentrics
and if i do do a fast eccentric like say
i'm doing a barbell curl
and i go down very fast how do you know
if the muscles are doing the work or if
you're just letting gravity
do a lot of it yeah and that's the real
interesting thing that
um so number one you you
describe the force velocity curve well
and there has been
some good evidence showing that um that
when you move
faster it actually has greater effects
on the hypertrophic response
uh and on strength now again some
limitations of that research
specifically that the bulk of that
research that i've seen is all on
using isokinetic i think it might be one
or two that's using that stunt but it's
virtually all using the isokinetic
dynamometer as the kinetic machinery
which again does not necessarily
as mentioned does not necessarily
translate to
isotonic training whether the tension on
the muscle there might be other factors
uh i do think the most important thing
again is the control aspect i don't
think you need to lower a weight like
this
as a matter of fact i i think that's
probably a negative for the most part
but uh unintended you just do it very
quickly
the muscle is not doing any of the work
at that point you're not lowering
the muscle needs to be forced to lower
the weight
and if you're not allowing the muscle to
lower the weight whether that's a second
two seconds
and by the way the other issue with some
of the research is they've studied the
extreme ranges
so they've studied a very fast versus a
very slow
and they haven't looked at what about an
intermediate slow
this is where you have to start to try
to piece together things use some logic
um and again to me i don't think the
time
is nearly as important as just making
that muscle do the work
now so you and i both agree that you
don't need to do super slow eccentrics
but
i have used that in my own training and
with clients before
for example with the bench press i don't
load it up to 130
like studies show you're 30 stronger
with eccentrics
but i will load it up to say a one rep
max so they are going to do their one
relax i will lift it off for them say
the bench press
i have them lower it very slowly i don't
count
i just tell them to lower it slowly and
then i'll maybe have them do three reps
with their one rep max lowering it under
control
and i found that to work well for if if
you haven't done it
and you do that for your bench you can
see some
some extra gains you know if that's if
you have a spot or a competent spotter
i should add but you believe there's a
time in the play and place for things
like that
i do i mean i i think it's something
that uh
didn't you write an article on that you
wrote an article on the scj right
yeah well i didn't discuss the tempo as
much but yeah
i do uh you you need to allow you need
to
um make the muscle do the work now how
slow
i actually have experimented that
actually is an area where i've
experimented not necessarily with the
tempo like you said just making them
lower
slowly whether that is more effective or
less effective
i i've not seen any research on uh super
maximal negatives
as far as the timing of them goes yeah
you could load up to 130 and just have
them they would lower it a lot slower
but try they're trying to resist is
but that's what for athletes kind of get
that stimulus when they do plyometrics
and things like that you get this high
force
eccentric loading when you catch an
olympic lift or when you you know
um but uh well and the final point i'd
make on that
which again is you wouldn't get this
from research but sometimes just doing
we
kind of mentioned this with a variety
aspect just doing different things that
the
uh that hit works the muscle in a
different manner
can facilitate greater gains tapping
into other mechanisms
okay we've got a couple minutes left
last topic super slow
training so there's
there's slowing it down and then there's
super slow training which
i um if i recall correctly that's
a 10 second concentric repetition and a
five-second
negative repetition now
uh this there's a some some of the
younger
listeners won't know this but super slow
when did the book super slow come out
like 90s
it was in the early 90s early 90s
and there are still a lot of proponents
for super slow training
and i i someone the other day um
dan ogborn posted something on twitter
if you want to get blasted just
talk about tempo and watch the super
slow people come after you so
as lane norton would say come at me bros
um
i bring it on guys yeah i i will say
that super slow we'll post this to the
super slow
forums and and look at the hate mail
that we get
but their argument would be
that well first of all they would say
that research supports it
in which case i disagree they would cite
the article you talked about
but that had flawed methodology because
it
it looked at a slower tempo outcome
but let me explain that that's an
important thing
we can't just gloss over that so the
what the super soul people hang their
hat on was a 1995 study by
wayne westcott it's actually a
combination of two studies he did where
he did a
a two uh 204
kind of the nautilus protocol so six
second
uh rep versus a 15 second rep so 10
seconds up
five seconds down and what he did was is
that he then tested them he tested the
six second group on a six second two
second four second down
i think it was a ten rep max and he
tested the um
super slow on a five rep doing it at at
very slow reps now
what is the issue with that well anyone
knows that if you're used to doing
something
as most people don't have as much gains
to get out of it so if you do
they're uncoordinated the beginning when
you have to lift something very slowly
it's an uncoordinated thing because
you're not used to doing
it's something that you're just you're
going to be incredibly weak you do some
training
and you'll get way better at it so the
margin will be a lot bit bigger right
so they they would say that there is
that research does support it but if you
read the entire body of research and
i've
over the years i've come across lots of
articles
comparing faster versus slower tempo and
i would say faster
up to a point faster has an advantage
with
strength hypertrophy power and even
metabolic responses as well would you
agree well that's with super slow
training
it's across the board that really the
only study that i have seen
and i think there's been one other that
i don't think it was published that it
was a poster
uh study that gave support to super saw
the fact it wasn't published would say
something
but uh but yeah i mean there's been
actually multiple studies that have come
out for strength for power for
hypertrophy
schweinke just did looked at one for
both strength and hypertrophy
uh and metabolic that's correct that the
uh
faster repetitions the traditional burns
more
utilizes more energy so really it's it's
a no
no-brainer and and what's the other
thing the logical fallacy super slow
says that
well you're going to reduce momentum
when you're lifting well
if you're just looking at that there's
been a study that shows that after two
seconds beyond two seconds
there is no additional benefit to
slowing down as far as momentum yeah
like quasi-static
yeah is 98 right i have studies with
that too
um so one last point then we got to go
because we're at 32 minutes i think
um a lot of the super slow people would
say
for training the elderly this is
important because
they're they don't need jarring on their
joints but i think you and i would both
agree that the elderly
they lose power they they lose power and
functional strength so give them
there's no reason why they can't do box
squats and
rdls with a broomstick if you have to
and then
slowly add weight but you can give them
glute bridges and function
like exercises that are going to build
their hip extensors and build their keep
their quad mass and keep their
function and power so you don't need to
purposely slow it down for that group
there's ways to have joint friendly
training that
is still more functional and transfers
more to their activities of daily life
do you agree
yes and i'll give you one recent study
just done
with it one second up three seconds so
basically an explosive concentric
three seconds down versus three seconds
up three seconds down in the elderly
showed much greater functional
improvements after it was eight or
twelve weeks
uh in 65 plus year old
subjects with no issues as far no
differences in injuries between groups
so that it did not have any negative
outcome measures
awesome so okay so to summarize tempo
um depends on the exercise
some trainers have employed it some of
our
friends have employed it with success i
personally am not a big fan of it i
think it can interfere
uh so are you but we do believe that you
should try to focus on the feel
and make sure you're feeling the muscle
if you're training for hypertrophy for
athletes you should explode
you should use different types of
exercises and drills for example heavy
lifts
and the intent should be to move it as
fast as possible even if it's slow
that was by research by sale and beam
classic research by salem beam that
shows that it's the tent you might not
move fast but it's the intent to move
explosively
that makes that ensures that you're
firing your that you're
recruiting all your motor units and um
so and utilize heavy lifting explosive
lifting plyometrics things like that
to make sure you're you know developing
your power and rate of force production
and
your stretch shortening cycle and all
that and what else
don't do super slow training
do you agree i agree anything else to
add
well and just that i certainly i know
you are too we're both
open towards changing our opinions if
evidence comes out and certainly like i
said the research because of certain
limitations
makes it difficult but just from a
logical perspective it's hard to see
why why or how uh counting
your reps and focusing on a given time
really is going to have
significant benefits so i'm certainly
open hopefully that
that research will come out and we can
do another podcast
okay thank you very much for watching um
we are going to conclude now if you we
we like to see reader comments
and uh or listen or comments and we also
uh are open to we we always just we
never know what we're gonna do until
brad comes up with an idea
two days before we we record these and
so
you've got ideas we'd like to hear them
thank you very much